<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-02-22T20:49:14+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Milind Shah</title><subtitle>This blog is a way for me to learn Markdown and share my thoughts, opinions, ideas, online tools, books, movies, parks &amp; museums. Occasionally, I might post photos from my travel experiences possibly with trip itineraries and hyperlapses when I experiment with the camera.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Structured Job Search</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2022/02/22/job-search.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Structured Job Search" /><published>2022-02-22T20:20:20+05:30</published><updated>2022-02-22T20:20:20+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2022/02/22/job-search</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2022/02/22/job-search.html"><![CDATA[<p>Managing your job search can seem like a huge project, but with the right approach and tools you’ll be able to do this effectively and efficiently.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Online tools can help you stay aware of job opportunities as they are published.</li>
  <li>Networking both online and offline can help you expand the reach of your job search.</li>
  <li>Use basic management approaches to track your job search from start to finish.</li>
</ol>

<p>Check this video:</p>

<iframe width="800" height="450" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/8SugsUe0VbY" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Transcript:</p>

<p>When you’re looking for a job, there are many websites and tools available online to help you.
The trick is working out what’s best for your job search.
It is important to set up your job search and keep track of it
so that you save time and find the right job faster.
Before diving in, take a moment to think about the kind of work that you’re interested in 
so that you can really focus your search.
Pick three industries you’re interested in and 
then choose a few companies that appeal to you most within those industries.
With this list in mind, set up Google Alerts to get the latest news and articles 
about these industries and companies delivered straight to your inbox.
You might spot unexpected job opportunities and you’ll also look well informed at interviews
when you can talk about the latest industry developments.
Next up are online job boards. Use a search engine to research these.
there are many available so try taking the same approach as before
and choose the two or three most relevant to you.
Keep in mind that over half of all job vacancies are filled by personal connections and word of mouth.
So while it’s important to apply for jobs online,
developing your network can also play a big part in your success.
Tell your friends, family and former colleagues about your job search.
Even if they don’t work in the industry you’re interested in,
they might be able to introduce you to someone who does.
Also consider attending industry events or conferences,
which is another great way to make new, relevant contacts.
Many companies and their employees post job opportunities on social media
before they appear on job boards, so it’s worth following their profiles on LinkedIn, Facebook and Twitter.
LinkedIn is the most work-focused social network online and will allow you
to connect with people based on their jobs or the industries they work in.
This means the content published and shared there is more likely to help your job search
just remember to keep your connections relevant and focused to your job goals.
Once you make contacts offline, remember to immediately add them to your LinkedIn network
while the connection is still fresh in both your minds
it’s a great way to keep conversations going.
You can also search for LinkedIn Groups relevant to the jobs you’re looking for.
Groups allow people with common work interests to come together and discuss industry developments,
as well as share interesting content and jobs.
If you have something valuable to add to the conversation, contribute to the group discussions
this can help you get your name out and perhaps even help foster new connections.
Once you start applying for jobs, it’s important to keep track of which roles you’ve applied to,
so you can follow these opportunities up in a timely manner.
All it takes is a simple spreadsheet using software like Google Sheets or Microsoft Excel.
Include the names of the companies applied to, their contact details,
the date applied, when to follow up and what the current status is,
“ongoing”, “waiting for a reply”, and so on.
Add a link to the job description for easy reference,
and remember to update this spreadsheet as your job search progresses.
You could also set up a similar spreadsheet for your contacts,
listing their name, company, contact details, how you connected, and whether you need to follow up with them.
So that’s how to save time and find the right job faster.
Remember to work out which kind of job or industry is right for you,
then focus your online search on the relevant jobs
and keep connecting with people who can help make your plans a reality.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Managing your job search can seem like a huge project, but with the right approach and tools you’ll be able to do this effectively and efficiently.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Preparing for Job Interview</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2022/02/22/prepare-job-interview.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Preparing for Job Interview" /><published>2022-02-22T20:20:20+05:30</published><updated>2022-02-22T20:20:20+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2022/02/22/prepare-job-interview</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2022/02/22/prepare-job-interview.html"><![CDATA[<p>Coming to your job interview prepared, relaxed and informed can be the difference you need to really make that lasting impression.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Anticipate questions you may be asked.</li>
  <li>Stay relaxed during the interview.</li>
  <li>Demonstrate your motivation for the role after the interview.</li>
</ol>

<p>Check this video:</p>

<iframe width="800" height="450" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/VUHHuc4hev4" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Transcript:</p>

<p>Landing that all-important job interview is an exciting moment
and a big step towards realising your goal.
In this video, we’ll share a few tips on preparing for the big day,
staying relaxed during the interview itself
and leaving a lasting impression that will help you stand out from the crowd.
Preparing yourself for a job interview can be the difference between giving in to stress
and impressing your future employer.
Treat the interview as a conversation between two people
rather than as a series of formal questions and answers.
It’s a chance for both your potential employer and you to decide if you are the right fit for each other.
With that in mind, let’s take a look at some things to think about before the big day.
First, research the company and job you’re being interviewed for and ensure you’re clear
on what the role involves, the skills required and why you would make the best candidate.
Always walk into an interview knowing how to articulate how you can add value to the company,
and if possible, with examples of how you can help answer their needs.
It’s also worthwhile to try finding out in advance who will be interviewing you,
so that you can tailor your approach to their needs.
For example an HR manager will often look for different skills
than, say, your potential line manager, so try to imagine what is important to them.
Next, try to anticipate the questions you’ll be asked.
Here are some of the most common interview questions,
but be sure to research whether there are any questions particular to your industry or role:</p>
<ol>
  <li>What can you tell me about yourself?</li>
  <li>Can you list your strengths?</li>
  <li>What weaknesses do you have?</li>
  <li>Where do you see yourself five years from now?</li>
  <li>Why do you want to work here?</li>
</ol>

<p>When thinking about your answers, make sure you don’t go straight to the solutions
but you always tell a story where you explain your thought process.
Including data and concrete examples will help you prove your points.
Prepare your answers in advance and practice delivering them out loud
so that you can approach the big day with confidence.
It’s also worthwhile to prepare questions to ask during the interview.
Not only will this help you learn more about the job that’s on offer,
but it will also show potential recruiters that you’re highly interested and engaged.
Remember that interviewers are most impressed by candidates who can think on their feet
and ask for clarification where needed.
Right before you head into the interview, focus on staying calm and relaxed.
Arrive early and take a moment to gather your thoughts.
Taking deep breaths and exhaling slowly will also help relax your body and mind.
During the interview, bear in mind 70% of your communication is nonverbal.
So remember to keep eye contact, smile, sit up straight and jot down relevant notes.
Also, try not to cross your arms, as this can come across as defensive.
After the interview, consider sending a quick ‘thank you’ email to the interviewer,
which will demonstrate your professionalism, that you appreciate their time
and how much you really want the job.
As well as thanking the interviewer for their time,
use the email as an opportunity to showcase your understanding of the role.
End with a friendly and clear sign off, such as “I look forward to hearing from you”,
or something similar.
With these tips, you’ll soon feel fully prepared
and ready to make a great first impression on your future employer.
Good luck!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Coming to your job interview prepared, relaxed and informed can be the difference you need to really make that lasting impression.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Develop your personal brand</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2022/02/22/personal-brand.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Develop your personal brand" /><published>2022-02-22T17:09:58+05:30</published><updated>2022-02-22T17:09:58+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2022/02/22/personal-brand</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2022/02/22/personal-brand.html"><![CDATA[<p>Recruiters often have to sift through piles of applications before shortlisting their candidates. 
So what can you do to make sure you stand out from the crowd?
Developing a solid and authentic online presence can help you engage recruiters 
and give them a clear and accurate indication of who you are.
Utilise social media, blogs and online communities to strengthen your personal brand and online identity.</p>

<p>Check this video:</p>

<iframe width="800" height="450" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/GZ9PHAXyZ00" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Transcript:</p>

<p>The secret to standing out to recruiters is to present yourself as unique and authentic
in person, on paper, but more and more importantly, online.
One needs to create and manage a personal brand online
that will successfully reflect who they are.
Your personal brand is the combination of personal attributes,
values, strengths and passions that people know and value you for
it’s the perception others have about you based on the sum of your actions.
A strong personal brand is intentionally cultivated, authentic,
and allows you to communicate your strengths.
In today’s connected world, the management and promotion of your personal brand online is key.
Research shows that most recruiters will check your social media presence to learn more about you,
and after employee referrals and company websites, social media is the most important recruiting tool.
So it’s clear why delivering your brand genuinely and consistently
will help you stand out in today’s marketplace.
Embracing the right social media channels will give yourself the best chance of being found.
Think about what really interests you and in what areas you would like to be seen as an expert.
Based on your passions and interest, choose up to three topics to focus on.
Next, identify the most relevant sites or Social media platforms related to your topics.
For example, if you want to become a foodie influencer,
your target audience is most likely to be on a visual platform like Instagram or Pinterest.
Or to give people insight into your business experience in IT,
focus on building your LinkedIn profile
and sharing relevant industry-based content other members would find engaging.
In addition to social accounts,
consider having a personal website to help build your online presence.
A website allows you complete control over what is published,
and can also help your name rank in search engine results.
When it comes to publishing content, you don’t have to do it all at once.
Aim to be consistent in the quality of what you post and set time to do this regularly.
But remember it’s not just about creating and publishing content,
building a strong network of connections for your own brand can also be greatly beneficial to your job search.
Always ensure that your personal brand is authentic and a true reflection of who you are.
Now, it’s time to get started creating and managing your personal brand online.
Think about how you can put your best foot forward to impress recruiters
and start exploring which channels are the best fit for your online presence.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Recruiters often have to sift through piles of applications before shortlisting their candidates. So what can you do to make sure you stand out from the crowd? Developing a solid and authentic online presence can help you engage recruiters and give them a clear and accurate indication of who you are. Utilise social media, blogs and online communities to strengthen your personal brand and online identity.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">CV &amp;amp; CL</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2022/02/22/cv-and-cl.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="CV &amp;amp; CL" /><published>2022-02-22T16:39:53+05:30</published><updated>2022-02-22T16:39:53+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2022/02/22/cv-and-cl</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2022/02/22/cv-and-cl.html"><![CDATA[<p>A CV or covering letter is often the first impression you get to make with prospective employers, 
so it’s critical these documents make a mark.
Whether you’re delivering your story on paper or on an online platform like LinkedIn, 
you will need to include some key points so that your story comes across clearly and persuasively.</p>

<p>CVs and covering letters are often the first opportunity to impress potential employers, 
so it’s critical they’re done well and tailored to the job you’re going for.</p>

<p>Be sure to include the following:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Contact information</li>
  <li>Previous work experience</li>
  <li>Qualifications</li>
  <li>Education</li>
  <li>Personal motivation statement</li>
</ol>

<p>Check this video :</p>

<iframe width="800" height="450" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/u6Fu0CT4lzY" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Transcript:</p>

<p>Think of your CV as a written summary of your personal, professional and social attributes
that proves why you’re the ideal candidate for a job.
While there are no official rules for how it should look,
here are some key points you’ll definitely want to include.
Your contact information, such as your name, phone number and email.
A summary section at the top, describing in 2-3 sentences who you are and what you have to offer.
Details of your previous work experience, including company names, job titles, and start and end dates.
Add a brief summary of your roles and achievements
that emphasise the skills required for the job being applied for.
You’ll also want to include details of any diplomas, certificates or exams you’ve passed
along with the dates and possibly grades if this information is relevant for your industry.
A good practice is to keep your CV limited to only the most relevant and recent information
and share it in a PDF format. 
Make sure your CV stands out, and always tailor your CV to the job you’re applying for.</p>

<p>In summary, here are tips for writing a great CV.</p>
<ol>
  <li>Keep it concise and clear, placing the most important and recent information at the top.</li>
  <li>Remember to proofread for correct spelling and grammar.</li>
  <li>Avoid overuse of formatting, such as bold, italics or underlining.</li>
  <li>Stay clear of jargon that won’t be understood by your potential employer
such as acronyms and company specific terms.</li>
</ol>

<p>Depending on the kind of jobs you’re applying for, you could also consider creating another type of CV
like a LinkedIn profile, or even a personal website.
LinkedIn is a great place to both boost your visibility to employers and connect with likeminded professionals.
When creating a LinkedIn profile, ensure your headline is clear and simple
and use the summary section to include a mix of the past, present and future ambitions.
You should make the most of recommendations from a previous employer or colleague,
and publish these on your profile.
When it comes to describing your previous roles - ensure you focus on skills 
relevant to the job you’re looking for and showcase that you have the relevant experience.
Remember to keep your profile up to date.
That shows potential recruiters you’re organised and passionate about what you can offer them.
Now you’ve completed your CV, it’s time to write a formal covering letter.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A CV or covering letter is often the first impression you get to make with prospective employers, so it’s critical these documents make a mark. Whether you’re delivering your story on paper or on an online platform like LinkedIn, you will need to include some key points so that your story comes across clearly and persuasively.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Land your next job</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2022/02/22/land-your-next-job.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Land your next job" /><published>2022-02-22T16:27:16+05:30</published><updated>2022-02-22T16:27:16+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2022/02/22/land-your-next-job</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2022/02/22/land-your-next-job.html"><![CDATA[<p>Before you embark on landing that dream job, take a moment to reflect on what you really want from your new role. Knowing this can help you identify what to look for throughout your job search and put your best foot forward.</p>

<p>Check this video from Google:</p>

<iframe width="800" height="450" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/lki06ICavRk" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Transcript:</p>

<p>Whether you’re starting out in an industry for the first time
or are ready for your next challenge,
the first step when looking for a job is defining what is important to you.
Finding that perfect job requires identifying your skills 
and learning how to tell your story to potential employers.
Start by thinking about what you enjoy 
and which industries or companies would suit you best.
If you could list five things you want from a job, what would they be?
Do you love helping people learn, or enjoy working with numbers-
or perhaps you want a position that offers flexible hours?
To get to know yourself better, ask your friends, family and colleagues
which words they think describe you best and what your greatest strengths are.
Personality tests can also help you recognise the traits that come to you naturally.
Once you’ve defined what your dream job could look like,
the next step is to identify the skills you have to offer.
Begin by writing down your qualifications, academic achievements
and ‘hard skills’- things that can be defined and measured,
like a diploma in accounting, years of experience in web design,
or a degree in nursing.
Next, pinpoint what makes you valuable to a company-
beyond your work experience or qualifications.
For example, leadership, teamwork and communication skills
describe how you interact with others.
These ‘soft skills’ are becoming more and more important across all industries 
and are worthwhile highlighting when applying for a job.
To help shortlist your main skills, 
think of both challenges and successes you’ve encountered in the past,
and consider which skills helped you in these situations the most.
After identifying your skills, it’s time to think about
how you will persuade potential employers you’re right for the role.
This will come across in your CV and cover letter,
or might happen naturally during the course of an interview.
Though a request like “Tell me about yourself” may seem quite general and unstructured,
keep in mind what the interviewer is really asking for:
insights into your professional experiences,
and more specifically, how you could add value to that particular role.
Instead of presenting yourself as a series of facts,
organise your previous experiences into a story.
The best stories follow a clear structure and take readers or listeners on a journey-
so keep this is mind when telling your own.
Highlight your greatest professional accomplishments.
If you are new to an industry, feel free to take general success stories from your life-
just make sure that you focus on the transferrable attributes
relevant to the position being applied for.
For example, a personal achievement at university
or a volunteering role can be used to demonstrate
your great communication or problem solving skills.
Remember to highlight why you want the job
and show your potential employer how motivated you are to work for their company.
To wrap up, try to remember these top tips when crafting your pitch to employers:
Identify keywords that best illustrate your skills and abilities
Highlight any relevant professional or academic achievements,
add numbers to make your story more tangible
for example, “3 years experience in web design”, or
“in my previous job, I succeeded in reducing yearly costs by 25%”
Tailor your pitch to each role, and review the job description carefully
to ensure you address the company’s needs.
Now you’re ready to show potential employers why its you they should hire!
Taking these first steps will steer you in the right direction
and help you identify which jobs would be the best fit for your talents.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Before you embark on landing that dream job, take a moment to reflect on what you really want from your new role. Knowing this can help you identify what to look for throughout your job search and put your best foot forward.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome to my Jekyll-powered Blog!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2022/02/22/welcome-to-jekyll.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to my Jekyll-powered Blog!" /><published>2022-02-22T11:30:06+05:30</published><updated>2022-02-22T11:30:06+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2022/02/22/welcome-to-jekyll</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2022/02/22/welcome-to-jekyll.html"><![CDATA[<p>Hello World!
Currently I am reading this book: <img src="https://source.unsplash.com/MvLRTUqOdvo" alt="A book about hope by Mark Manson" /></p>

<p>I maintain a reading list and bookshelf online at <a href="https://goodreads.com/computingfreak">Goodreads</a></p>

<p>This week I plan to watch this movie on Netflix : “Downfall : The case against Boeing”</p>

<iframe width="800" height="450" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/vt-IJkUbAxY" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>I maintain a movie watchlist online at <a href="https://letterboxd.com/computingfreak">Letterboxd</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Hello World! Currently I am reading this book: I maintain a reading list and bookshelf online at Goodreads This week I plan to watch this movie on Netflix : “Downfall : The case against Boeing” I maintain a movie watchlist online at Letterboxd]]></summary></entry></feed>